A Guide to the Rockefeller University records, Business Manager, Correspondence, Series 2 FA808
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller University records, Business Manager, Correspondence, Series 2
1903-1912 (scattered items to 1919)
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research
Rockefeller University
FA808
1.14 Cubic Feet 3 letter document boxes.
1 volume and 3 boxes.
File Plan note
Former Classification: I 210-2
Other Finding Aids
FA811 Rockefeller University records, Business Manager, Henry James Subject Files, Series 1.
FA137 Rockefeller University records, Business Manager, Subject Files, Series 3.
FA809 Rockefeller University records, Business Manager, Annual Reports, Series 4.
FA810 Rockefeller University records, Business Manager, Budget Histories, Series 7.
Arrangement
Alphabetical.
Scope and Contents
Individual and institutional correspondence.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
Operations management; Medical research; Life sciences; Hospitals; Medical technology; Cell and biomolecular sciences; Medicine, Preventive; Prevention and health; Biology -- Research; Vivisection; Biochemistry
- Business Manager Correspondence, 1903-1912 (scattered items to 1919); 2; 1 volume and 3 boxes
  Scope and Contents note
  Includes some of the Institute's earliest correspondence in regard to grants, experimental animals, vivisection, serum production, experimental work and business matters including (2 inches) York & Sawyer file regarding construction of the Hospital. Includes administrative letters written by Simon Flexner, members of the Scientific Directors, administrative officers and a few by Jerome Greene. One volume copy-book (1905-1906) mostly by Simon Flexner. Names included are listed below.
  Arrangement note
  Arranged in chronological order in volume, in alphabetical order in boxes.
  - Abderhaldern, Emil (Box 1)
  - Abel, John J. (Box 1)
  - American Bacteriologists (Wm. H. Park) (Box 1)
  - Adami, J. George (Oskar Klotz) (Box 1)
  - Barker, Lewellys F. (Box 1)
  - Bashford, E.F. (includes background for proposed International Association for Cancer Research) (Box 1)
  - Billings, Frank (Nomination to National Academy of Sciences) (Box 1)
  - Evaluation of new Michael Reese Hospital) (Box 1)
  - Billings, John S. (infection from books and cards in Astor Library) (Box 1)
  - Burton-Opitz, R. (Box 1)
  - Castle, W.E. (Harvard - regarding mice cages and animal breeding) (Box 1)
  - Cone, Claribel (Box 1)
  - Conner, Lewis A. (Box 1)
  - Combs, Carey (Box 1)
  - Coiner Akademie (Box 1)
  - Councilman, W.T. (Regarding grants; hardships for medical researchers) (Box 1)
  - Corwin, R.W. (Colorado Fuel and Iron Co. Use of Carrel-Dakin method in industrial accidents) (Box 1)
  - Cooke, Morris L. (Box 1)
  - Congdon, Edgar D. (Box 1)
  - Congdon, Ernest A. (Box 1)
  - Cordova, Rudolph de (Box 1)
  - Crampton, Henry E. (Box 1)
  - Crane, Marion (Box 1)
  - Creasy, R.C. (Box 1)
  - Crile, George (Box 1)
  - Crince, Mary (Box 1)
  - Critic and Guide (Box 1)
  - Crouch, Henry (Box 1)
  - Craighead, E.B. (Tulane University) (Box 1)
  - Crowley, Howard (grant) (Box 1)
  - Curtis, John G. (Vivisection) (Box 1)
  - Cushing, Harvey, 1906-1913 (Box 1)
  - Cummins, G. Wyckoff (1910 letter re death of child from polio and illness in chickens) (Box 1)
  - Cusachs, P. (Box 1)
  - Cutting, R. Fulton (1906 formation of Committee for clean milk in NYC) (Box 1)
  - Dabney, Charles W. (1908-1909 President, University of Cincinnati) (Box 1)
  - Dakin, H.D. (Box 1)
  - Darling, S.T. (isthmian Canal Commission) (Box 1)
  - Davenport, C.B. (Carnegie Institution) (Box 1)
  - Davidson, Andrew (Box 1)
  - Davidson, M.T. Co. (Box 1)
  - Dawson, John L. (anti-dysenteric serum) (Box 1)
  - Dickson, E.C. (grant) (Box 1)
  - Doughty, Howard W. (grant) (Box 1)
  - Doyle & Sons (Real Estate 67-68th Sts.) (Box 1)
  - Dowling, M.A. (artist) (Box 1)
  - Dunham, Carroll (Bussey Institution) (Box 1)
  - Dunham, Edward K. (Box 1)
  - Dunham, Theodore (Box 1)
  - Eagleton, Wells P. Recommendation for Dr. Martland) (Box 1)
  - Early, John R. (Leprosy case) (Box 1)
  - Edsall, David L. (Medical developments at University of Penn) (Box 1)
  - Eiseman, O.N. (grant) (Box 1)
  - Elkins, Stephen B. (Check to Rufus Cole) (Box 1)
  - Elsberg, Charles A. (appointment at Institute with Meltzer) (Box 1)
  - Embree, Edwin Rogers (possible replacement for Jerome Greene) (Box 1)
  - Ernst, Harold C. (Journal of Medical Research) (Box 1)
  - Ewing, James (see also Bashford) (Box 1)
  - Famulener, L.W. (grant) (Box 1)
  - Farrand, Livingston (Association for study and prevention of TB) (Box 1)
  - Faust, Edwin Stanton (Box 1)
  - Field, Cyrus (Box 1)
  - Fischel, W.E. (Box 1)
  - Fischer, Martin H. (Box 1)
  - Fisher, Irving (Box 1)
  - Flick, Lawrence F. (Box 1)
  - Fordyce, John A. (Box 1)
  - Foster, Nellis B. (Box 1)
  - Gay, Frederick P. (Box 1)
  - Gaylord, Harvey R. (cancer research) (Box 1)
  - Gillespie, Louis J. (Box 1)
  - Goldthwait, Joel E. (Box 1)
  - Goldmann, Edwin Allen (Box 1)
  - Gorham, George E. (Bender Hygienic Lab.) (Box 1)
  - Halsted, W. ?, S.? (Box 1)
  - Haring, H.A. (Box 1)
  - Hartwell, John (Box 1)
  - Herter, Adele (Mrs. Albert) (Box 1)
  - Hodenpyl, E. (Box 1)
  - Hodgkins Fund Prize (Box 1)
  - Holt, Cutice N. (Box 1)
  - Hornsby, J.A. (refers to Jobling) Hospital Bureau of Standards Houghton, Henry S. (Box 1)
  - Howard, L.O. (Secretary AAAS) (Box 1)
  - Howard, W.T. (Box 1)
  - Interstate Commerce (transport cost of small animals) (Box 1)
  - Jackson, Holmes C. (Box 1)
  - Jacobson, C.A. (Box 1)
  - Jahresbericht (Box 1)
  - Jennings, H.S. (Box 1)
  - Jensen, C.O. (Box 1)
  - Jesse, R.H. (Box 1)
  - Johns Hopkins Endowment (Box 1)
  - Jones, Harry (Johns Hopkins University) (Box 1)
  - Jordan, David S. (Stanford University) (Box 1)
  - Kanlbaum (Chemische Fabrik) (Box 1)
  - Kelly, H.A. (Walter Reed Memorial) (Box 1)
  - Kendall, Arthur (Box 1)
  - Kerolene Inhaler Breese Co. (Box 1)
  - Kinghorn, Hugh M. (Box 1)
  - Kinyoun, J.J. (Box 1)
  - Kirkbride, Mary Butler (Wadsworth, Augustus) (Box 1)
  - Klotz (Box 1)
  - Knickerbocker Press (Box 1)
  - Knoop, F. (Box 1)
  - Knopf, S.A. (Box 1)
  - Kny-Scheerer Co. (imported glassware) (Box 1)
  - Koch, R. (Box 1)
  - Koch, Waldemar (Box 1)
  - Koechl & Co. (Box 1)
  - Kossel, A. (Box 1)
  - La Forge, F.B. (Letters from P.A. Levene and Pshorr) (Box 2)
  - Lamb, George (Plague Research Commission) (Box 2)
  - Lange, Mort ("Nellie"; Carrel) (Box 2)
  - Lee, Frederic S. (Anti-vivisection) (Box 2)
  - Leitz, Ernst (Box 2)
  - Lemcke & Buechner (Periodicals) (Box 2)
  - Levaditi (Box 2)
  - Levin, I. (Box 2)
  - Lillie, Frank R. (Wood's Hole: Dr. Loeb) (Box 2)
  - Lillie, Ralph S. (Box 2)
  - Lilly, Eli & Co. (Box 2)
  - Lippincott, J.B. (Box 2)
  - Locke, Edwin (Box 2)
  - Loevenhart, A.S. (Box 2)
  - Louisville Research Laboratory (Box 2)
  - Lower, W.E. (Box 2)
  - McCormick, H. (child of E. Hoos) (Box 2)
  - McDonald, M. (Box 2)
  - McFarland, Joseph (Box 2)
  - MacCurdy, John T. (Box 2)
  - MacDonald, Arthur (Penal reform) (Box 2)
  - Mabee, O.R. (Box 2)
  - MacLaurin, R.D. (Box 2)
  - MacCallum, W.G. (Dochez, R.) (Box 2)
  - Mall, F.P. (Box 2)
  - Malta fever (Box 2)
  - Mandelbaum, F.S. (Box 2)
  - Manning, W.J. (Box 2)
  - Mark, E.L. (Box 2)
  - Marks, Lewis Hart (Prof. Ehrlich) (Box 2)
  - Martinez, Gonzalez I. (Box 2)
  - Matas, (Tulane University) (Box 2)
  - Maury, J.W. Draper (Box 2)
  - Mayer & Müller (Box 2)
  - Mayo. Earl (Box 2)
  - Meyer, Mas (Box 2)
  - Milne, Lindsay S. (Box 2)
  - Mills, Albert J. (Box 2)
  - Mitchell, S. Weir (Box 2)
  - Morgan, H. de R. (Box 2)
  - Morgenroth, J. (Box 2)
  - Much, Hans (see also Muensterberg, H.) (Box 2)
  - Muensterberg, H. (Amerika Institut) (Box 2)
  - Mulford, H.H. Co. (anti-dysenteric serum) (Box 2)
  - Munn, (Kissinger-Yellow fever) (Box 2)
  - Murlin, J.R. (Box 2)
  - National Assoc. for Advancement of Colored People (Box 2)
  - National Municipal League (Box 2)
  - Neufeld, F. (Box 2)
  - New Era Printing Co. (Box 2)
  - New York Academy of Medicine (Box 2)
  - New York Milk Committee (Box 2)
  - Neuman, Leo H. (New York Medical Society; anti-vivisection) (Box 2)
  - Niccole, M. (Box 2)
  - Nichols, H.W. (Box 2)
  - North, Charles (Respiratory Commission) (Box 2)
  - Norton, Charles D. (Acoustic patient; reference to Wallace C. Sabine) (Box 2)
  - Noyes, Arthur A. (Allan W. Rowe) (Box 2)
  - Nuttall, George H.F. (Box 2)
  - Oertel, Horst (Russell Sage Institute) (Box 2)
  - Olmsted Brothers (Elm Trees) (Box 2)
  - Ophüls, W. (Box 2)
  - Osborn, Henry F. (Box 2)
  - Osgood, Robert B. (Box 2)
  - Osler, William (Box 2)
  - Osterberg, Emil (Box 2)
  - Pathology (Charles W. Howard, William H. Tytler. Henry K. Marks) appointments (Box 2)
  - Pearson, L. (TB in cattle) (Box 2)
  - Pennsylvania Academy of the Fine Arts (Box 2)
  - Phipps, Henry (Box 2)
  - Phipps Institute (founding; invitation to S. Flexner to be on advisory council) (Box 2)
  - Playground (Box 2)
  - Poliomyelitis (Box 2)
  - Pritchett, H. (Carnegie Foundation) (Box 2)
  - Public Service Commission (Noise from river traffic) (Box 2)
  - Publicity (Box 2)
  - Reichert (Microscopes) (Box 2)
  - Remy, 'E. (Rabies) (Box 2)
  - Reynolds (Box 2)
  - Ricketts, H.T. (Box 2)
  - Rockefeller Sanitary Commission (Box 2)
  - Rosenau, M.J. (Box 2)
  - Ross, George W. (Box 2)
  - Ross, R. (Use of anti-dysenteric serum in India) (Box 2)
  - Roux, -.-. (Pasteur Institute; bust of Pasteur) (Box 2)
  - Rouileer, C.A. (Box 2)
  - Rowe (Box 2)
  - Ruffer, -.- (Box 2)
  - Ruh, Harold O. (Box 2)
  - Rush, T.E. (Box 2)
  - Russell Sage Institute of Pathology (Box 2)
  - Ruth, E.S. (Box 2)
  - St. Clair- Abrams, Alex (Box 2)
  - Salant, William (Box 2)
  - Schorer, Edwin H. (Box 2)
  - Schulte, Hermann von W. (Box 3)
  - Selling, Laurence (Box 3)
  - Shaklee, A.O. (Box 3)
  - Shiga, K. (Box 3)
  - Siegel, J.H. (Box 3)
  - Simon, Charles E. (Box 3)
  - Six-O-Six (Salvarsan) (Box 3)
  - Skinner, Edward H. (Box 3)
  - Slye, Maud (Box 3)
  - Smithsonian Institution (Box 3)
  - Sophian, A. (Dallas, Texas meningitis outbreak (Box 3)
  - Stine, Charles M.A. (Box 3)
  - Stevens, A.R. (Box 3)
  - Studies (Box 3)
  - Symmers, Douglas (Box 3)
  - Syracuse University (Box 3)
  - Taylor, A.E. (re Nobel prize 1908) (Box 3)
  - Thomas Bond (Clyde property) (Box 3)
  - Thompson-Starrett Co. (Box 3)
  - Tuberculosis (Committee on Prevention; Municipal Commission) (Box 3)
  - Underhill, Frank P. (Box 3)
  - United States Fidelity & Guranty (Bonding of employees) (Box 3)
  - University Press (publications) (Box 3)
  - U.S. Dept of Agriculture (Milk study) (Box 3)
  - Uhlenhuth, -.- (syphilides in monkeys) (Box 3)
  - Vincentini, Filandio (Box 3)
  - Wacker, George Leonhard (Box 3)
  - Wadley & Smythe (Box 3)
  - Walker-Gordon Laboratory (Clyde property) (Box 3)
  - War Department (arrow poison, Flexner Commission, report on typhoid by Capt. F.F. Russell) (Box 3)
  - Warthin, Aid red Scott (Peyton Rous fellowship) (Box 3)
  - Weeks & Sons (Builders of Founder's Hall) (Box 3)
  - Wells, H.G. (Box 3)
  - Wenz & Mackensen (monkeys) (Box 3)
  - Werner and Winter (W.T. Howard monograph) (Box 3)
  - Whipple, George C. (Box 3)
  - Whistling of boats in East River (Box 3)
  - Williams, Herbert U. (Box 3)
  - Williams, J. Withridge (Box 3)
  - Wistar Institute (Box 3)
  - Wolbach, M.D. (Box 3)
  - Wolcott, Herbert (sleep grass) (Box 3)
  - Wolff-Eisner (re. publication of handbook on serumtherapy) (Box 3)
  - Wood, Edward J. (Box 3)
  - Wood, F.C. (Box 3)
  - Woods, W.A.E. (Box 3)
  - Wood's Hole (building of laboratory for Dr. Loeb) (Box 3)
  - Woodward, R.S. (Carnegie Institution. Noguchi vol. on snake venom) (Box 3)
  - Wyman, Walter (advisory board of Hygienic Lab.) (Box 3)
  - Yale and Towne Mfg. Co. (Box 3)
  - York & Sawyer (Hospital construction. Includes letter from J.D. Rockefeller Jr. dated 6/25/1910 accepting revised plans) (Box 3)
  - Zeuner, (Translation of report on TB) (Box 3)